Today's daf דף daf is Mem Gimmel מג. Mem Gimmel. We're going
to spend the today's daf דף daf taking apart the statement of
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel about different aspects about a shutaf שותף, shutaf, about
a partner in a field. And the first point that Shmuel שמואל
Shmuel made, he said a couple of things. He said, 'Yored bireshut
יורד ברשות,' Yored bireshut, when he's working the field, it's assumed that
he has permission from his partner, which the Gemara גמרא Gemara wanted
to understand if that meant that basically it would not be a
chazakah חזקה, chazakah, it would not be adverse possession, and which is
certainly the position of the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, but it goes against
another position of Shmuel שמואל Shmuel that it is considered a chazakah
חזקה. chazakah. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara made distinctions under certain cases
it is, certain cases it isn't. It isn't categorical. It depends on
what that sort of indicates given the sort of norms and the
context of the society. But now we're going to look at the
rest of Shmuel שמואל, Shmuel, which is not going to have to
do with chazakah חזקה, chazakah, but be fascinating in its own right,
which is number one, what does 'Yored bireshut יורד ברשות' Yored bireshut
mean other than the issue of chazakah חזקה? chazakah? Number two, he
said that a shutaf שותף shutaf can be me'id מעיד me'id on
his friend—on his fellow partner's portion in the field, which seems bizarre.
I mean, there's like 'ein lecha nogeya b'edut gadol m'zo אין לך
נוגע בעדות גדול מזו,' ein lecha nogeya b'edut gadol m'zo, you know,
you're totally a vested party. And then the third issue is that
they're shomer sachar zeh l'zeh שומר שכר זה לזה, shomer sachar zeh
l'zeh, if they're watching the field of the other half of the
field or the other half of whatever it is they're watching, they're
treated as a shomer sachar שומר שכר. shomer sachar. So let's take
a look. So we pick up at the bottom of... and excuse
me, I seem to have a frog or something in my throat.
Although we're done with that parshah פרשה parshah in the Torah תורה,
Torah, right?
Frogs, tzfardea צפרדע, tzfardea, early-mid-late for the parshas פרשות. parshas.
All right.
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this: 'Shutaf שותף shutaf hai...
hi Bobby.' Okay, so 'gufa גופא.' gufa. You know what? I think...
could you go into the bathroom and get me some paper towels
or something? Oh, you have that? Oh, forget it, forget it.
Sorry.
All right.
All right, sorry. All right, thank you. No, I really need a
tissue, Bobby. All right.
Coffee's fine. Okay, let's go. Gufa
גופא. gufa.
Five lines from the bottom, six lines from the bottom on Mem-Bet
Amud-Bet מב עמוד ב. Mem-Bet Amud-Bet. Amar Shmuel אמר שמואל: Amar Shmuel:
'Shutaf k'yored bireshut dam שותף כיורד ברשות דמי.' Shutaf k'yored bireshut dam.
A shutaf שותף shutaf
who goes and works the field is like he has permission. Mai
kamashmalan מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashmalan? What does this teach us? Shutaf
v'shutfut ein lo chazakah שותף ושותפות אין לו חזקה? Shutaf v'shutfut ein
lo chazakah? If it's only there to teach us that there's no
chazakah חזקה chazakah like the Mishnah משנה Mishnah at least in some
cases, so why not just say what you mean? You know, mean
what you say and say what you mean. Leima 'Shutaf ein lo
chazakah לימא שותף אין לו חזקה,' Leima Shutaf ein lo chazakah, say
it. So...
I understand, but for that phrase, so that phrase of 'k'yored bireshut
dam כיורד ברשות דמי' k'yored bireshut dam it must mean something more
than just 'ein lo chazakah אין לו חזקה.' ein lo chazakah. So
Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה: Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha: lomar she'notel b'shevach
hamagiya l'ktafayim לומר שנוטל בשבח המגיע לכתפים, lomar she'notel b'shevach hamagiya l'ktafayim,
b'sadeh she'hi בשדה שהיא—which b'sadeh she'hi is apparently the original girsa גרסא—u'v'sadeh
girsa she'eina asuya lita k'sadeh asuya lita ובשדה שאינה עשויה ליטע כשדה
העשויה ליטע. u'v'sadeh she'eina asuya lita k'sadeh asuya lita. So it says
something beyond normal questions of chazakah חזקה, chazakah, something unrelated to chazakah
חזקה. chazakah. A normal sippur סיפור: sippur: here we are,
Bobby and I are partners in a field, and Bobby's away and
I think that we need to do some stuff in the field.
I plant a whole orchard of... of what do you call it?
Of orange trees, or I go ahead I harvest the whole field.
You know, Bobby's not around. So the question is I here now
worked or I plant, you know, grain in it, I worked this
field without her explicit permission. So how much do we sort of
say? Well, you know, she was a partner in it and you
needed her permission, and if not it's like you went ahead and
you worked your neighbor's field without permission. So what would be the
halacha הלכה halacha if I were to work my neighbor's field without
permission? So the halacha הלכה halacha is like this: somebody who is
'yored l'sdeh chavero יורד לשדה חברו,' yored l'sdeh chavero, I go into
Micah's field here, he's not my shutaf שותף, shutaf, he's just my
neighbor or who knows, some stranger, and I decide I'm going to
go ahead and do something that I see this field needs. Micah
lets his grass way overgrow, it's a disgrace to the neighborhood, I'm
going to go ahead and I'm just going to mow his lawn
for him. I'm going to go ahead and I'm just going to
plant his field with trees because I think that that's what it
needs. So the halacha הלכה halacha is that if it is a
type of a thing that we can all agree was sort of
necessary for that field and fit for that field to be done
to it, then he gives me, pays me the standard fee. Now
what is the standard fee? So there's a whole debate about this,
but anyway Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says the standard fee is like what
you would pay a kablan קבלן, kablan, what you would pay somebody
to do the whole job, like you know, fixed fee for mowing
the lawn, 50 bucks, go ahead, fine. How much are you going
to pay to plant it? X amount. So if I went ahead
and did it and we could agree that it was 'asuya lita
עשויה ליטע,' asuya lita, it needed to have that done to it,
then even though there's no agreement, Micah pays me the fee which
is very bizarre. Then if you're very enterprising, you know, and you
have a... you're in the lawn mowing business, you just go around
to everybody's overgrown field and you collect after the fact. You know,
so it's a little bit funny that I... so the whole discussion
that maybe I can't collect like the high fees of that, you
know, maybe a low fee of that, but actually that's a halacha
הלכה. halacha. That's when it's 'asuya עשויה'... asuya But when it's sort
of we can all agree that it needed it. But let's say
we can agree it didn't need it.
And I go ahead in Michael's field, where normal people plant wheat,
I decide it would look really nice if there were some olive,
some olive trees there. And I go ahead and plant,
or whatever, it's just not the normal thing that that field would
be used for and I go ahead and plant olive trees. How
much does Michael owe me? So that case is a case of
like יורד שלא ברשות. yored she-lo bi-reshut. One is שלא ברשות she-lo
bi-reshut when we could agree that it was needed where you pay
me some low end of a standard contracting fee, and a pay
of שלא ברשות she-lo bi-reshut is Michael pays me the lesser of
either my expenses or the improvement of the field. Okay, but not
the standard type of a contracting fee. Those are all the cases
where... no, it's the lesser of those two. It won't be more.
The lesser of the expenses and how much it improved. The expenses
is always going to be lower than my fee. My expenses are...
my fee includes my expenses plus my profit. Okay, anyway, so that's
the general הלכה. halacha. So in this case where it was the
case of a שותף, shutaf, it was me and Bobby, even though
Bobby didn't give me permission, we assume that since I'm working on
the field that belongs to us jointly, it's like I have permission.
So what are the implications of it's like I have permission? So
let's take a look now back again at this line. Okay, so
there's again a whole question how to read this line. That's why
there's a big תוספות, Tosafot, but the line says the following: אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה לומר שנוטל בשבח המגיע לכתפים. Amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha lomar she-notel be-shevach ha-magia le-ktafayim.
So number one is you get the שבח, shevach, the improvement of
the field that reaches the shoulders. Now what does that mean that
it reaches the shoulders? So one way that רש"י Rashi and the
רשב"ם Rashbam explain it means that it was ready to be harvested
and I went ahead and I harvested it, and I'm going ahead
and get like I said, like a normal fee as if I
had permission, not as if I was doing it without permission. Now
what exactly the חידוש chiddush is that it's ready to be harvested
is not so clear. תוספות Tosafot has another fascinating explanation of that
phrase which he goes back and forth on, but I just want
to share it, which is
שבח המגיע לכתפים shevach ha-magia le-ktafayim doesn't mean that the produce has
reached shoulder height. It means that it's a type of a harvesting,
it's a type of extracting benefit from the field that required me
to put like, you know, my... what's the phrase, put your back
into it? So put your shoulder into it. Meaning that it required,
it wasn't just like the trees ripened by themselves and I didn't
have to do anything, the fruit ripened. I actually was מגיע לכתפים.
magia le-ktafayim. It came because I used some, you know, I used
some of my... you know, I put my back into the work.
Okay, I think that's the closest English expression I can come up
with it. Anyway, so, okay, fine. That's all very interesting. What does
that mean? What's the חידוש chiddush there? So basically, I'll read it
according to תוספות. Tosafot. The חידוש chiddush is that he reads it
this way. He reads it as scenario number one is it is
a שדה העשויה ליטע. sadeh ha-asuyah le-ita. It is something that needed
that work. Okay, so if it was a stranger whose field I
would work and it needed that work, right, it was עשויה ליטע,
asuyah le-ita, I would get paid but I said before, I'd get
paid the job of a קבלן. kablan. The job of a fixed
fee for the whole thing, which is like at the lower end
of the spectrum. Because I am a שותף, shutaf, I get paid
not as a קבלן, kablan, but I get paid as an אריס.
aris. I basically take half of the benefit. Somebody who is a,
you know, I get a higher percentage of the benefit of what
I put into it. Okay, so that's point number one. And point
number two is, and some read this all as one point. Meaning
I... the whole field, you know, one acre, I work it. Fifty
percent is mine, fifty percent is Bobby's. So for the fifty percent
that's mine, I get a hundred percent of the profit. For the
fifty percent that's Bobby's, I get fifty percent of the profit. Because
if Bobby were to hire a sharecropper, that's what the sharecropper would
get, which is more than if she were to hire just a
contractor. A contractor you give them a thousand dollars flat fee. A
sharecropper spends more time there, is given explicit permission to be there,
again as opposed to somebody who's doing it without permission, and gets
a higher rate. Okay, so the focus of this first point is
that if you're working a field that needed it, again, I don't
know how he reads it into those words, but whatever, I'll just
tell you what תוספות Tosafot says. What it means is maybe that's
the first of המגיע לכתפים ha-magia le-ktafayim that you put your back
into it. You know, somebody who was there on a... like a
more serious basis, like a sharecropper is there on an ongoing basis
as opposed to a contractor comes in, does the job and leaves.
Okay, so you get number one because even though I didn't have
Bobby's permission, I get on her half of the field, you know,
for her fifty percent, like a sharecropper, a serious percentage of it.
Number one. Number two, ובשדה, u-be-sadeh, there's a addition of a ו,
vov, ובשדה שאינה עשויה ליטע כשדה העשויה ליטע. u-be-sadeh she-einah asuyah le-ita
ke-sadeh ha-asuyah le-ita.
Number two is even if it was a field that normally most
people would assume did not need this to be done to it.
Okay, this was a wheat field and I decided that it needed
to have orange trees in it. Okay, so in that type of
a case, if it was Michael's field I did that to, Michael
would pay me some bare minimum for my labor or whatever, okay,
because it was not a normal thing that that field would be
used for. you could expect somebody would want. But if it's our
field that we share in partnership, so because I have I guess
a certain degree of authority to decide for it, but normally it's
supposed to be a joint vote. You know, maybe, you know, but
since I do have a presence here, a 50% stake, you know,
therefore, I actually, it's like I have permission to do that. And
actually, Bobby would actually owe me for planting her half of the
field as if it were a normal thing to plant orange trees
in this field. Which is a pretty funny הלכה, halacha, right? You
could imagine like an irresponsible partner who has crazy ideas, right? You're
partner with somebody in the field and they're this person that always
has these like
harebrained ideas about, 'Oh, you know, we could make a lot of
money if we planted orange trees.' And I say, 'You're totally crazy,
it makes no sense.' And then I go away for vacation, I
come back and they plant orange trees. You know? What? Meaning if
you would have like, you're just sitting around looking at it, no,
אינו עשוי ליטע eino asui lita means it's not a normal thing
to be done. And not and this person now has planted orange
trees in the whole field, and now I actually have to pay
them, you know, as if I had hired them to do that
for having done it on my half of the field.
Yeah, well, okay,
let's not deal with that case. Anyway, it is strange. That does
seem to give a lot of autonomy to, you know, a שותף,
shutaf, you would actually think it's the, you know, you can't go
ahead and do stuff jointly on a field we own jointly without
my permission. Okay, so anyway, that's anyway, but that's the חידוש chidush
of that last line, שאינו עשוי ליטע she-eino asui lita as if
it were עשוי ליטע asui lita and therefore he gets a certain
fee for doing it on my half of the land as well.
Okay. And in the first part, where he talks about, talk about
Gamaliel defining that, is that only if we know she wouldn't have
done anything? Like, let's say she would have put in the work.
Oh, I don't know, but I think so. Anyway, all right, let's
keep on going. Okay, so that's hard to unpack, that's why there's
a long תוספות Tosafot and it deals with other סוגיות, sugyot, but
we get at least the general sense of that. Okay, now we
get to what the focus of the גמרא Gemara is going to
be, at least for the first עמוד. amud. ומעידים
זה לזה. U-me'idim zeh l'zeh. Now this is the stuff that makes
even less sense, which is Bobby and I are here, joint owners
of a field. Now when I say, by the way, to clarify,
Bobby's half, I don't mean there's a line down the middle of
the field. Then we're not partners. Then she owns half of the
field, you know, this the north half, I own the south half.
I mean we jointly own it equally. Right? We jointly own it.
But like in the previous case, I planted the whole field, so
50% of what I did, not in a specific area, was being
done, you know, she was her portion of it. Okay, so but
so now we have this field that we own jointly, and David
comes and David basically says, 'That whole field is mine, and here's
my proof, whatever, that I own the field and that Dov and
Bobby don't own the field.' And I'm now going to bring witnesses,
you know, I'm going now to testify that that field actually belongs
to, you know, to me and Bobby. So let's say I can't
testify it belongs to me because obviously I'm a direct party, but
at least I can bring together with another witness can testify that
at least half of it belongs to Bobby. And that we can
join up to, to, you know, contradict David's proof that it's his.
So the question is that's crazy because if I'm able to, you
know, to be a witness to benefit Bobby, well, benefiting Bobby is
benefiting me, right? Because, you know, again, it's not like the field
is divided, you know, the north side and the south side. So
if you have rights to that field, that's going to impact, you
know, my, you know, me as well. And if I push you
away even from Bobby's portion of the field, that's going to help
protect my interests. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara
says אמאי? Ammai? נוגעין בעדותן. nogei'in b'eidusan.
You have a direct benefit in terms of this testimony. If you
look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, נוגעין בעדותן, nogei'in b'eidusan, because כל זמן
שלא חלקו, kol zman she'lo chilku, as long as they didn't divide
it completely, if David takes
any of the land from the field, they'll both lose. I'm not
just testifying for Bobby, I'm testifying for both of us. Anything that
David takes from the field, he's not taking just from Bobby, he's
taking from both of us. Their field isn't divided between Bobby's half
and my half. So any how can I testify to protect Bobby?
Protecting Bobby is protecting me.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן? Hecha b'mai askinan? What
are we talking about? בכותב לו דין ודברים אין לי על שדה
זו. Bekosev lo din u'dvarim ein li al sade zu. So David
basically goes to brings a proof that it's his field. Now I
have, you know, can be testifying that it's
not. But so in order to allow me to testify, what I
basically do is I give away my ownership of the field. Okay,
I forfeit to Bobby my ownership of the field, which makes me
no longer a vested no longer an interested party, in the sense
now it's all Bobby's field. You know, I remove myself from any
rights to it and therefore, since I'm no longer an interested party,
I can testify.
Now, that is has raises a couple of questions. The first of
course being, which is that maybe the whole thing is a trick.
Right? For the time being, I'm going to forfeit my portion in
the field and then after we sort of win it back from
David, then Bobby will give me back my half of it. Right?
He'll write it back to him. What? It's like a wink, you
know, you actually wrote it down. I understand I wrote it
down. But you need it with the, with two witnesses, עם שני
עדים, im shnei eidim, now. Right, right, could be. But you know,
nevertheless, you know, should we be concerned about that? Okay, so that's
sort of like, that's I think what occurred to us as the
first major concern, which is, how am I allowed to do this,
right, then anybody would always do this, you'll come to defend your
partner by writing away your portion, by forfeiting your portion, and then
every partner will always testify to defend the other partner by doing
this, and then get it back afterwards. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
doesn't directly address that, it'll implicitly address that in a minute, but
that's not the immediate concern of the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
says, וכי כתב ליה מאי הוי, ve-ki katav lei mai havei, how
does writing I have no claim to this field work? Okay, because
I'm a part owner in it. The way I give up my
ownership is not by renouncing my claim, it's not a claim, it's
an actual ownership. The only way I will no longer own this
field is by selling it or giving it. So I would have
to actually write a gift to Bobby or a sale. I sell
my half of this field to Bobby for one dollar and give
her that שטר. shtar. That's what I'd have to do. To say
I renounce my claim, you don't renounce a claim on something you
own, you give away something you own. Okay, so it's a, fine,
that's just a technical problem, so we'll find another way to say
it. But anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara question. והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught
in the ברייתא, Baraita, האומר
לחבירו דין ודברים אין לי על שדה זו, ha-omer le-chavero din u-devarim
ein li al sadeh zo, I have no claim on this field,
ואין לי עסק בה, ve-ein li esek bah, I have nothing, no
dealings with it, וידי מסולקת הימנה, ve-yadi mesuleket heimena, my hand is
removed from it, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, that's meaningless, because
you didn't actually give away your portion. Okay. Now by the way,
I should point out parenthetically that I just explained it the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam did, that the difference is that if you're an
owner, you can't say I don't have a, you know, I have
no claim, you have to actually say I am granting my portion,
I'm giving away, I'm selling my portion. But another read that the
רשב"ם Rashbam suggests, which he doesn't like, but he suggests, is that
the problem isn't whether you use the term I have no claim
versus I'm giving, but it's whether you use the past or the
future. If you say I have no claim, that's describing a current
state of affairs, okay, and that's not true. You actually do have
a claim, you do have a stake. I have no stake, that's
not true. But if you were to say, if you were to
say I shall,
I will not have a stake, like it's clear that you are
intending to make a change of affairs, I hereby renounce my stake,
then actually there's a, a way of reading it that that would
be acceptable. The problem is not saying I do or I don't
have a stake, the problem is saying in the present, which is
a description of facts, as opposed to I hereby do not, which
is a declaration of a change of state. Okay, it's sort of
like when a man, you know, marries a woman, right, when he
says הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, so, you know,
בטבעת זו. be-tabaat zo. So what's the function of the הרי? harei?
Why didn't he just say את מקודשת לי? at mekudeshet li? Because
if you were to say את מקודשת לי, at mekudeshet li, you're
just describing a, you know, facts. You are married to me. But
you're not married to me! Right? We're under the חופה, chuppah, hoping
it's going to happen soon, but it's not, you know, it's not
true that את מקודשת לי. at mekudeshet li. הרי, harei, behold, by
this ring you will be married to me, you shall be married
to me. That's the function of the word הרי. harei. It makes
the statement into like a, a functional, an operative statement, right? There's
a word for that, meaning not declarative but, there's some technical word,
performative type of a statement. Okay, anyway, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says
maybe that's a difference, but the רשב"ם Rashbam thinks no, I don't
care if you said I don't have a stake, I shall not
have a stake, I hereby do not have a stake, none of
that works. You're an owner, and the only way you stop being
an owner is by actually transferring your ownership. So the גמרא Gemara
says fine, so let's say you do that. So the גמרא Gemara
says הכא במאי עסקינן כשקנו מידו. hacha bemai askinan k'she-kanu mi-yado. Fine.
You didn't just say I hereby don't have a stake, you actually
did a קנין. kinyan. I say to Bobby, Bobby give me a
handkerchief, she gives me a handkerchief, and I say, by taking this
handkerchief, I hereby transfer to you my ownership of this field. Now
I no longer own the field, and now I can serve as
a witness about that field. So the גמרא Gemara says,
וכי קנו מידו מאי הוי, ve-ki kanu mi-yado mai havei, הרי מעמידה
בפני בעל חובו. harei ma'amida bifnei ba'al chovo. So the גמרא Gemara
says, still, even before we get to any concerns about that we've
got a little scheme going on here. By the way, just because
we have a scheme doesn't mean I'm testifying falsely, right? I mean,
could be that I really am testifying honestly, but nevertheless I'm doing
it by, you know, by freeing myself from ownership of the field,
which I'm then going to reclaim. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
before we even get to that, I have my own, then I
will still benefit from getting rid of David and testifying against David.
How will I benefit from that? Because think about what happened. Think
about what could happen. I borrowed money here from Joe. I owe
Joe a thousand dollars. Joe has a lien on this piece of
property that Bobby and I jointly own. Joe can seize half of
it, right, my half of it, you know, for his, for his
loan. Can't seize Bobby's half, but he can seize my half. I
go ahead and I give this loan... I give my half to
Bobby. So can Joe still seize that half of the property? Not
anymore. Yes! He has a lien on it. It's property. I mean,
if I don't have cash
available. If I have assets available he can get it from me
but if I don't he can still get it from Bobby. Now
let me help now that's if I sold it to Bobby. Let's
say instead of selling it to Bobby David proves this was never
our field to begin with it was always his field. Can Joe
take it from David? No. So even after I have granted my
half to Bobby it is still I am still a vested party
I am an interested party in getting rid of David cause that
field I still benefit from the fact that it was my field
that I transferred to Bobby. That allows me מעמידה בפני בעל חוב.
ma'amida bifnei ba'al chov. I can present it to Joe my creditor
and he can collect my debt from that field. So even though
I don't own it since I did own it and now it's
Bobby's that means that that is a more advantageous position for me
to be vis-a-vis that field than for it to have never been
mine. So how can I testify against David if I still am
a beneficiary of that testimony? Okay. So the Gemara says וכי תימא
ידע מה הוי הרי מעמידה בפני בעל חוב. vechi teima yeda mah
havei harei ma'amida bifnei ba'al chov. I can still use this field
even if it's no longer mine that my creditor can now collect
from it. So דאמר רבין בר שמואל משמיה דשמואל. de'amar Ravin bar
Shmuel mishmei deShmuel. המוכר שדה לחברו שלא באחריות. hamocher sadeh lachaveiro shelo
beachrayut.
If you sell a field, so I go ahead and I sell
my field here to Michael without אחריות achrayut meaning that אחריות achrayut
means that if somebody takes that field away and shows that it
wasn't mine or a creditor takes it away or whatever Michael אחריות
achrayut is insurance. I will reimburse Michael for his loss. So even
if I sold it to him if I sold it to him
with אחריות achrayut I certainly have a vested interest in testifying to
keep the field in Michael's possession right because now somebody comes and
says David here who's always claiming fields are his all the time
he comes and he says that field is his I've got a
vest if I sold it to Michael with insurance I certainly can't
testify against David right because by if if David wins I'm going
to have to I'm going to have to pay Michael's insurance claim.
So by getting rid of you I'm protecting my own interest. Okay
so with אחריות achrayut I certainly can't testify to get rid of
David. But even שלא באחריות. shelo beachrayut. So therefore if David would
take it away from Michael I would not have any I would
not owe Michael any money. Even in that case I can't testify
against David. Why not? שלא באחריות אין מעיד לו עליה. shelo beachrayut
ein me'id lo aleha. I cannot testify to say it belongs to
Michael and not David even though it's not mine anymore and even
though I won't owe Michael anything מפני שמעמידה בפני בעל חוב mipnei
shema'amida bifnei ba'al chov because by getting rid of David and keeping
it in Michael's hands Joe here my creditor can collect it from
Michael and have his debt paid off. But if David proves that
it was always his and not Michael's I would not be able
to pay off my creditor with that land. So having a land
that went through me to somebody else it remains I remain an
interested party and I cannot testify because that still becomes something that
there are could be liens on and therefore could be used to
pay off my creditors. Yes. So is the phrase מעמידה בפני בעל
חוב ma'amida bifnei ba'al chov the ה hei at the end of
מעמידה ma'amida is it the קרקע karka field? Yes. Oh so he's
just he's really maintaining the field for himself so to speak בעל
חוב? ba'al chov? Well no not for himself but if my creditor
would come I could present it to my creditor. You want to
be debt paid off? Go take Michael's field. Go take the half
of the field I sold to Bobby. I present it to my
creditor as the place where the creditor can collect from. Okay it's
not mine anymore but it was mine and having been
mine proved testifying to it prevent a person from being able to
do that? Well I mean we don't we don't have anything against
the person but because he has the opportunity he could do that
that makes him an interested party. And an interested party cannot testify.
Okay I can't testify that this field is Michael's and not David's
because I benefit from that testimony. Because you benefit because if it
was never if it was always David and never and not Michael's
then my creditor couldn't collect from it but because it's now Michael's
which means it also was once mine my creditor can collect it.
And in other words but the advantage then is that my debt
is then paid off? Correct. That's a שבח. shevach. Correct, yes. What
if a liens only on land? Yes. I mean there are some
exceptions about עבדים avadim or whatever but yes. So then like if
the partner sells his portion and then Joe comes after me and
says you know and if he doesn't he's unable to get a
lien on the property then can he come to me for the
cash that I've received for that in other words I have. Well
the creditor always first comes to me. So by the way that's
an interesting point meaning cause you could say one minute this might
depend on circumstances let's say I can prove that I never borrowed
money from anybody.
Let's say I have tons of assets and therefore there would never
be a need for me to my creditor to. to go collect
the liens from that other person, right? So wouldn't all those types
of cases right say well in this case I can prove that
I'm not a vested party. Is that enough? Or do we say
that it doesn't matter, since hypothetically you are entwined with this, and
there are ways in which somebody who once had the field benefits,
that's enough to invalidate you. So that's like an interesting quest- I
said that's sort of along the lines of what you're asking, right?
If in this particular circumstance I can demonstrate that I don't benefit
from it. But if he really benefits? If he's going to sell
the field, he's got to get some something for giving it to
this other party. So if he sells it, then any of his
assets could pay off Joe. Just I mean Joe would have to
come to me, right? Not to Bobby or, the other hand, the
partner. Yeah, yeah, but what you're basically saying is that let's say
that I actually have a lot of liquid assets, can maybe then
I should be allowed to testify? Because we're not afraid that my
creditor will come collect the field. Right, so correct. So it seems
like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not concerned about that. Either because
we can't figure, we have to just adopt one general rule, it's
maybe would in theory be true that if you could prove that
you would not be considered a vested party, but we can't start
trying to get to the bottom of that in every case. Or
maybe the status of being a vested party has to do with
the hypothetical possibility and not with the actual possibility. But you are
right that not every case will I benefit from this, from this.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Now I thought you were
going to ask another question which is is that if I do
have אחריות *achrayut* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to get
to this, if Joe will go ahead and collect it from Bobby,
let's say I gave it to Bobby. But if Bobby can now
get reimbursed from me because she lost it, then maybe I don't
benefit at all, right? Because now it's just transferring who I owe
the money to, right? So Joe gets it from Bobby and now
I have to pay back Bobby for what Joe took. So that's
actually, so there are in those types of cases, do I really
benefit or not from the fact that the field, even if the
field was never mine, was always yours, so then I owed Joe
the money, he couldn't go collect it from Bobby. So now the
field was mine, he collects it from Bobby, so now I owe
Bobby the money to reimburse her. What's the gain? So that's exactly
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to get to. It should
it should have said בלא אחריות אפילו אם אחריות *belo achrayut afilu
im achrayut*, right? Well, we're going to see, it depends who the
אחריות *achrayut* is for. So let's read the next line of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר
*Amar*. So anyway we've got this question, how now can I transfer
the ownership to Bobby
and testify? Won't I be a beneficiary? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says הכא במאי עסקינן דקביל עליה אחריות *hacha bemai askinan dekabel lei
achrayut*
that I accepted liability when I sold gave my half to Bobby.
Now, how does that make me able to testify? So the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says אחריות דמאן *achrayut deman*? Liability for what scenario? אי
נימא אחריות דעלמא *ee neima achrayut dealma*, let's say it means אחריות
דעלמא *achrayut dealma* for the fact that
somebody went ahead and David here, that's called אחריות דעלמא *achrayut dealma*,
meaning David went ahead and it had nothing to do with me,
David claimed that he was always the owner. So I go ahead
and I sell it to Bobby for whatever and then I say,
or I give it to her for a dollar, whatever it is,
and I say, I will reimburse you if ever you lose it.
Now David is coming in saying, remember, David is the reason I
want to be an עד ed *eid*, and he's coming in saying
it was always mine. So if I have taken liability for reimbursing
Bobby if David takes it, then that's all the more reason I'm
a פסול לעדות pasul l'eidus. *pasul le'edut* because I'm protecting myself from
having that liability. Okay, so that's not the liability I accepted, I
do not have liability for that case. Okay, then and that maybe
should allow me to testify in that case. אבל *Aval*, here is
liability, אי נימא כל שכן דניחא ליה אלא אחריות דאתי ליה מחמתיה
*ee neima kol sheken denicha leh ela achrayut de'ati leh machmateh*, liability
for things that came on account of me, meaning Joe, my creditor,
is now seizing that field from Bobby, including my half of that
field. That was a liability that I was to blame for that
came through a debt that I owe. So now this is exactly
what we said before. Okay, I give my half of the field
to Bobby. I'm going to testify to get rid of David. Do
I benefit from this? Well, if David were to take the field,
I wouldn't have to reimburse Bobby, so I don't benefit from that
thing. Do I benefit from the fact that I am by testifying
that it's Bobby's allowing that field to be used as a with
to pay off my debt to Joe because he has liens on
it? So the answer here is I don't benefit because even if
Joe were to take it and I would pay off my debt
to Joe, that would just be exchanged with a debt to Bobby
because I have insured her
against to be reimburse her if that field is seized due to
a debt that I have. So in that type of a case
where it would just be exchanging one debt for another, now I
am actually able to testify. So this now is the הלכה halacha
*halacha*. I can testify in this field that David is trying to
claim was always his by transferring my half to Bobby. And the
fact that I can benefit that now my creditor can take that
field, by promising by obligating, not promising, obligating myself to reimburse Bobby.
If that ever were to happen, then I don't stand to gain
from that fact that that went through me. Because if it actually
turns out that it is taken to pay off a debt, I'll
just owe that same amount of money to Bobby. So since I
now don't gain from the fact that it went through me, I
can actually testify. What we are not yet worried about is the
fact that I'm just doing this temporarily and I'm just going to
get my half back after afterwards, which doesn't mean I'm lying, but
it just means like, you know, maybe I'm not really removing myself
from this field and I really will benefit because after we get
rid of David, I'm going to get back my half. There is
a gain in that scenario. Well, if Bobby's a nicer person than
Joe. Exactly. You get the creditor off your back. Well, but now
I have a new creditor in his place. So right, so that's
where the גמרא's Gemara going to get to later, not in this
case, but in another case, which is, you know,
הראשון קשה ללווה והשני נוח הימנו. harishon kasha l'lova v'hasheini noach heimennu.
Exactly. Bobby's a much nicer person than Joe. So if I owe
the money to Bobby, she'll be much nicer about it, right. Exactly.
Right.
So somehow we're bracketing that. Could you review briefly what's אחריות בעלמא
achrayut b'alma again? אחריות בעלמא achrayut b'alma is that not through any
money that I owe anybody else, that's David, somebody who claims that
the field was never mine. Some external reason that that field is
taken away. Okay. So that thing to protect her against external basis
of loss, right. All right. So let's take a look. So now
we continue.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
וכי מסתלק נפשיה מיניה מסתלק. v'chi mistaleik nafshia mineih mistaleik. Now, just
because you have basically removed yourself from it, is it really considered
that you genuinely removed yourself? So again, here's where the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, the גמרא Gemara never says this explicitly, but the רשב"ם Rashbam
says what the גמרא Gemara is bothered with besides that it has
textual evidence that seems to indicate that it doesn't work, but the
logic is, is that shouldn't we always be afraid that you're just
doing this temporarily and ultimately you're going to reclaim your stake? Okay.
Now, what's the evidence that that should not work? It's pretty good
evidence. דתניא. d'tanya. בני עיר שגנבו ספר תורה שלהן. bnei ir sheganvu
sefer torah shelahen. You have people of a town and their ספר
תורה sefer torah was stolen. Okay. אין דנין בדייני אותה העיר ואין
מביאין ראיה מאנשי אותה העיר. ein danin b'dayanei ota ha'ir v'ein mevivin
ra'aya mei'anshei ota ha'ir. Now, this is going to really you understand
הלכה-ically halacha why this is true? But it's going to make things
really hard. Okay. Everybody in the town saw the גנב ganav run
off with the ספר תורה. sefer torah. So let's bring the גנב
ganav for a דין תורה din torah in the town. We'll have
the judges of the town judge, the villagers of the town be
the witnesses. The only problem is everybody is a בעל דין. ba'al
din. Everybody has a because they all jointly own the ספר תורה.
sefer torah. So they all stand to gain from the testimony. So
the problem though is the only people who can be the witnesses
are the people who weren't there. You have to have strangers who
were going through the town. It's a real problem, right? How do
you prevent the guy from getting away with it? But you understand
הלכה-ically halacha what? But what did Bobby say? They have non-Jews who
were live in the town. Well, yeah. I understand. They're the only
people who could testify. You know, in the time of the ראשונים,
Rishonim, when
particularly in אשכנז Ashkenaz where women were involved in business, you have
a real problem because sometimes the only available witnesses were women who
are הלכה-ically halacha, פסול לעדות. And basically it led to the אשכנז
Ashkenaz within אשכנז Ashkenaz for them to basically say, okay, we're going
to accept what the women say not as testimony, but as evidence.
So the fact that a woman will come and testify to something
doesn't mean it works as a sort of הלכות עדות, hilchos eidus,
but it works as well, it's likely true because otherwise why would
somebody be coming and saying such a thing? Actually because the reason
I thought about this, there was a case that's come up about
there, you know, the more things change, the more they stay the
same. Going back 800 years in the time of the רשב"א, Rashba,
actually I think also in ספרדי Sefardi communities apparently, this idea of
women testifying. There was a case about a debate of
who seated is it in the שול. shul. That's my seat, no
it's my seat. But the debate was it was a seat in
the women's section. Okay. Now actually it's not the women's section because
in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim it was the בית כנסת
לנשים. Beis Knesses L'nashim. It was a separate room. But the only
people who could testify whose seat it had been were women. So
the question is you have to find a way to allow women
to testify. Anyway, so it's similar to this. The only people who
could testify are the people of the town and they're all נוגע
בעדות. nogei'a b'eidus. So that's הלכה, halacha, okay, that they can't testify.
So now don't go tell the גנבים ganavim this. They've got a
great way, you know, it's that's why you got to have a
really good lock on your ארון. aron. Okay. בני אותה העיר שגנב
להם ספר תורה שלהן אין דנין בדייני אותה העיר ואין מביאין ראיה
מאנשי אותה העיר. bnei ota ha'ir sheganav lahem sefer torah shelahen ein
danin b'dayanei ota ha'ir v'ein mevivin ra'aya mei'anshei ota ha'ir. Now,
ואם איתא, v'im issa, if it's true that the way you could
deal with this is by renouncing your claim, right, so why don't
we solve the problem that way? יסלקו בתרי מינייהו ולדון. yisalku bitrei
mineihu v'ladun. Let two people renounce their claim or be מקנה makneh
it, you know, sell it, grant it, whatever, and let them be
the judges, and let two other people or three
people let those two be the witnesses and then go for it
in front of other judges, or let three people then do it
and let them be the judges.
No. No, no, no. A ספר תורה Sefer Torah even if you
don't have a monetary ownership of the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, if
you are a townsperson, you are a beneficiary of the fact that
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah is in the town. You might not
have a monetary ownership, but because it's in your שול shul and
it's not in this guy who's this guy is claiming you all
sold it to me. And we're saying we didn't sell it to
you, you stole it. So if we're going to win and we're
going to prove that he stole it and keep it in the
שול, shul, we're going to be able to have a קריאת התורה.
Kriyat HaTorah. Now why don't you sort of say, mitzvot לאו להנות
ניתנו, lav lehanot nitnu, it's not considered הנאה, hana'ah, but apparently the
fact that we're able to have our regular שבת Shabbos services is
enough to make me a beneficiary and not a witness. Okay. So
if somebody owns an article, right, and somebody steals it from him,
and then he sees it, he can't be a witness? Correct. I
know. It sounds crazy, right? Now, again, in contemporary
בתי דין, batei din, I mean we've learned a lot of things
הלכה, halacha you say like can a real court case operate that
way? So in contemporary בתי דין, batei din, they deal very little
follow like technical הלכות חושן משפט. hilchos Choshen Mishpat. Like 95% of
the decisions are based on some combination of equity and פשרה peshara
and compromise and
דינא דמלכותא, dina d'malchusa, which is very funny because you also have
to go to a בית דין beis din and so on, but
mostly it doesn't deal with
technical דיני חושן משפט. dinei Choshen Mishpat. Right, so in that type
of a case you're right, how could the owner not be believed?
So alright, we'll accept it again, like I was saying before about
women, we'll accept it as evidence, not as testimony. But according to
real חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, that doesn't work at all. We totally
exclude the testimony. Anyway, so here the גמרא's Gemara saying is, there
is room to claim there would in general be a way to
renounce your claim and be a witness, but here it doesn't work
because you remain a beneficiary even after you've renounced your ownership claim.
Yes. Corresponds to if he goes to another city. Yes, so maybe
if you both renounce your claim and change your town, then it
could work because then you're not a beneficiary anymore. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. That's weird. You don't have to
own the ספר תורה Sefer Torah like you do like an אתרוג,
esrog, you know what I mean? Well, that's what it's saying. So
therefore you remain a beneficiary. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this.
Okay, תא
שמע ta shema come and hear. האומר תנו מנה לבני
עירי, Ha'omer tenu maneh livnei iri, אין דנין בדייני אותה עיר. ein
danin bedayanei osah ir. So basically, I basically said, I am donating
a thousand dollars to my city for general improvements in the town
to be determined by the officers of the town. Okay. Now, and
then afterwards, at least that's what some people are saying I said.
Now I'm denying I ever said it. Okay. Can you get the
townspeople to testify? You could understand how on the one hand, those
are the only people who know. On the other hand, you could
understand let's say the townspeople decide here's a rich person who never
gives anything to the town. So let's go ahead and testify that
he promised to give a million dollars to the town. Right? So
they're נוגע בעדות. nogaya b'eidus. So the הלכה is, in that type
of a case, you do not accept the testimony of the townspeople
because again, they stand to benefit. So אין דנין בדייני אותה עיר
ein danin bedayanei osah ir ואין מביאין ראיה מאנשי אותה עיר. ve'ein
mevi'in ra'ayah mei'anshei osah ir. אמאי? Amai? Now why? לסלקו בי תרי
נפשייהו ולדייני. Lisalku bei trei nafshayhu u'ledaynei. Let two people basically renounce
their claim of the benefit that will come from this person's gift.
Now that's not exactly clear. How do you renounce a claim of
the benefit from the gift? Whatever the gift is, if it's going
to be invested in some
public's type of good, they will indirectly benefit. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says well, maybe let them go ahead and give an equal gift.
But even if they give an equal gift, that doesn't mean that
they're not going to benefit from this gift. So it's hard to
understand how that will operate, but let's not worry about that right
now. Maybe let's say why don't we say let them do that?
So you see that that doesn't work. That we're afraid that we
don't allow you to remove yourself and then be a witness because
maybe we're afraid you'll just restake your claim afterwards.
So הכא נמי בספר תורה. hacha nami b'Sefer Torah. So gives a
very weak answer. No, no, no. When I say I'm giving this
money to the town for a benefit, I mean specifically for a
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. And that's why people cannot say they're renouncing
their claim because then they remain beneficiaries. But if I'm saying I'm
giving it for some other purpose and it was genuinely possible for
a person
to give up his claim in a way that he would not
benefit from what I have just done, then he actually could be
a witness. And we would not be afraid that after he testifies
whatever, I mean, let's say the guy who made the thing, listen
there, he's giving up his claim, he's renouncing his claim, he's going
to testify and we won't be and if he genuinely could renounce
his claim in a way that he will not be a beneficiary,
then he can testify and we're not afraid that after he testifies,
he's going to restake his claim. Okay. We're not going to be
afraid. So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע. ta shema. Let's come,
bring another proof that seems like no, we do not allow this.
האומר תנו מנה לעניי עירי, Ha'omer tenu maneh l'aniyei iri, I go
at least you guys are claiming that I said this in שול,
shul, I'm denying it. Okay, but your claim is that I said
I'm giving a thousand dollars to the poor of the town. Okay.
So in that case,
אין דנין בדייני אותה עיר. ein danin bedayanei osah ir. same point.
Nobody here can testify that that's what I said in שול shul
because you're all going to benefit. So now the גמרא, Gemara before
it gets to the fact of this question of renouncing your claim
says, what do you mean you're all going to benefit? Only the
עניים aniyim are going to benefit. So the גמרא Gemara interrupts this
for a second and says ותסברא. v'tisbra. The גמרא Gemara says עניים
שקלי דייני מפסלי? aniyim shaklei dayanei mifseli? Just because the עניים aniyim
will take the money, why should that invalidate the judges? The judges
aren't the beneficiaries. Now you might be thinking they might be indirect
beneficiaries we're going to get to that, but for now the גמרא's
Gemara focusing on direct beneficiaries. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא
אין דנין בדייני עניי אותה עיר ואין מביאין ראיה מעניי אותה עיר.
ella eima ein danim b'dayanei aniyei oso ir v'ein mevi'in rayah me'aniyei
oso ir.
The poor of the town cannot be the witnesses, and the poor
of the town cannot be the judges because they're beneficiaries. Don't worry,
we're going to revise that. But still the גמרא's Gemara. claim is,
why is that a problem? Why, if it's true that you can
renounce your claim and we're not afraid that you're going to reclaim
your claim, so why not do that? ואמאי נסתלקו בתרי מינייהו ונידיינו.
v'amai nistalku beitreina minaihu v'nidaynu. Let two of the people say, two
of the עניים aniyim say, we are not going to accept any
of the funds that Dove gave and we're going to be the
witnesses and let's do it. So you see we don't allow that.
Okay, we're afraid that afterwards they're going to restake their claim.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי בספר תורה. hacha nami b'sefer
Torah.
No
no no, I didn't סתם stam say a thousand dollars to the
עניים, aniyim, I said a thousand dollars for a ספר תורה. sefer
Torah. ואמאי קרי להו עניים? v'amai karei l'hu aniyim? So why did
I say עניים? aniyim? דקאי ספר תורה עניים אינון. d'ka'ei sefer Torah
aniyim inun. Because when you don't have a ספר תורה, sefer Torah,
what how what does it mean to be poor if not poor
in תורה? Torah? So therefore נעבעך, nebach, you're also poor this town.
I can't believe it doesn't have a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, you
know, I want to help the poor of this town. You're all
poor, so therefore I'm going to grant you a ספר תורה. sefer
Torah. Okay, ואיבעית אימא לעולם כדקתני, v'iba'it eima l'olam k'd'katani, עניים ממש.
aniyim mamash. Okay fine fine, forget that. Let's acknowledge that פשט pshat
here is the poor. But nevertheless, everybody is a beneficiary. Why is
everybody beneficiary, not just the poor?
ובעניים דרמו עלייהו. u'va'aniyei d'ramu aleiyu. Everybody here, it's the town's responsibility
to provide for the poor. So if I'm agreeing to give a
thousand dollars, I have now alleviated some of that burden that the
entire town shares. Which is why it's not just the poor that
can't be witnesses. Nobody can be witnesses, nobody can be judges because
I've alleviated everybody's burden by a thousand dollars. Okay now, but we
still have to ask our question. Why doesn't, you know, here, you
know, Nissan and David say, you know what, we are going to
pay our full share that we would normally pay even before Dove's
donation. So therefore they're not benefiting from my donation again, if it's
possible to renounce your claim and allow you to testify. And let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Okay. So ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it
eima, it says like this, ובעניים דרמו עלייהו והיכי דמי? u'va'aniyei d'ramu
aleiyu v'heichi dami? What's the case? אי דקצלו להו ליתו בתרי מינייהו
מאי דקצלו להו. i d'katz'lu'hu leis'u beitreina minaihu mai d'katz'lu'hu.
So if everybody has a fixed amount that they have to contribute,
so let two people here, let Nissan and David say, we are
still going to give our fixed amount, we are not going to
have our burden alleviated at all and therefore we are going to
renounce any benefit that comes from Dove's donation and we're going to
testify that that's what he actually said. So, you know what, maybe
that would work, okay, and as long as they continue to promise
that they're going to give the full amount.
Okay. So הכא במאי עסקינן דלא קצלו. hacha b'mai askinan d'lo katz'lu.
No no no, nobody has a fixed amount. We all have agreed
that based on the needs of the poor, we're going to divide
it equally or we'll divide it based on people's wealth, however we're
going to divide it. So once I've made since it hasn't been
pre-established how much everybody owes, once I've made a contribution, it alleviates
everybody's burden by that amount. I mean well, that percentage divided. So
that's the case where you cannot renounce your claim. Okay now, the
גמרא Gemara says ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'it eima, and if you want לעולם
דקצלו, l'olam d'katz'lu, actually there is a fixed amount. And nevertheless, even
people who promise to give the full amount cannot be witnesses against
me. Why? וניחא להו דכיון דרווח רווח. v'nicha l'hu d'keivan d'revach revach.
It's still good because even though Nissan and David here say they're
still going to pay their fixed amount, after I have now given
a thousand, let's say ten thousand dollars to the עניים, aniyim, we're
not going to be knocking on Nissan and David's door anytime soon.
We don't need that money right away. We've gotten now we're flush.
That's like רווח. revach. We're flush with funds in our, you know,
for the עניים. aniyim. So that also indirectly benefits them even though
they're still going to give their fixed amount, it's not going to
be as as urgently needed. And in this case there is no
way for them to renounce a claim. In this case they will
always benefit. The reality that the עניים aniyim need less money and
that we have less demands and there is, you know, they're always
going to be beneficiaries on that. I mean I guess you could
say let them give the full amount that they've promised up front,
you know, that might be a way in which, you know, in
which we free them. But the basic conclusion of the גמרא somewhere
I would say counterintuitively is that without these special cases of עניים
aniyim or ספר תורה, sefer Torah, even if you had a vested
interest, if you if you renounce your claim, give it up. transfer
it, you can now be a witness and we are not afraid
that you are now going to after you win the case go
ahead and get that and get your and get it back afterwards.
Yes, I keep on saying my mind, you think this is accurate,
but this could be dealing with the concept of it's impossible not
to be a beneficiary of public goods. If I live in a
town and there's a street, the land, the value goes down. Right,
that is correct. Right, yeah, that is clearly correct. Yes,
so רמב"ם *Rambam* based on ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* פאה *Peah* says that the
charity collection is not fixed and it's assessed by the charity collectors.
Right, well that's also, yeah, that's something we've seen before in general
earlier in בבא בתרא *Bava Batra*, some basic question about assessments. Now
I want to actually make an important point the ראשונים *Rishonim* make,
which is, all the ראשונים *Rishonim* ask a big question here, which
is, there's generally a principle which is, תחילתו בפסול וסופו בכשרות פסול
*Techilato Bifsol VeSofo BeKashrut Pasul*. It's basically
David and I here are related,
right, because he's my brother-in-law. All right, and therefore I see him
borrow a hundred dollars. I can't be a witness for him. Afterwards,
we're no longer related. I divorce my wife and he is no
longer with his sister, he's no longer my brother-in-law. I'm not allowed
to testify about him because when the event initially occurred, I was
פסול *pasul*. Okay, so here they all say, so why isn't it
the same thing here? Right, when it initially occurred, you were a
beneficiary, even if you renounce your claim and we're not afraid of
any scheme, okay, you initially were invalid, you should remain invalid. So
one answer the ראשונים *Rishonim* give, I'll just give you two of
the more interesting answers, one answer the ראשונים *Rishonim* give is
that there's a difference between if you look at תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*,
let's look at a little תוספות *Tosafot*, ויש לחלק בין תרי מיני
ולא דיינו *Veyesh lachlek bein trey minei velo dayanu*. ואם תאמר זו
היא דתנן תחילתו וסופו בכשרות techilaso vesofo be-kashrus? והכא הוי תחילתו בפסול
דמינטרי הוה פסול *Ve'im tomar zu hi detnan techilato vesofo bekashrut vehacha
havei techilato bifsol deminatrei hava pasul*. והוי כמו קרוב ונתרחק *Vahavei kimo
karov venitrachek*. You were a relative and then you became a non-relative.
ואומר רי דלא שייך תחילתו בפסול הכא כיון שאין פסול תלוי בגוף
אלא בממון *Ve'omer Ri delo shayach techilato bifsol hacha kivan she'ein pasul
taluy beguf ella bemamon*. Now what does that mean? It's not בגוף
אלא בממון *beguf ella bemamon*. It could be that's the formalist idea,
saying that I'm a relative is a status, where brother-in-law, that's a
personal status. Saying that I stand to gain from this type of
a transaction is not a status issue. So as long as it's
not a status issue, to be assessed at right now I don't
gain. Right if we put a label on me, relative, brother-in-law, whatever,
פסול *pasul*, that's like a פסול *pasul* label. But this wasn't a
label, this was just a, I stand to benefit. So that seems
to be one idea. Another way of saying this perhaps is, well
anyway maybe I won't nuance that, but let's just say that's one
approach. And more interesting approach is quoted in the name of the
ראב"ד Ravad *Ra'avad*. And this is really interesting. And that is to
distinguish between two concepts. One concept is called a בעל דין *Ba'al
Din* and the other concept is called a נוגע בדבר *Nogei'a BaDavar*,
right, the גמרא *Gemara*'s first line up is נוגעין בעדות *Nog'in Be'edut*.
The בעל דין *Ba'al Din* is the actual litigant. The נוגע בדבר
*Nogei'a BaDavar* is not the litigant, but the person who stands to
benefit, like more indirectly, from the case. Now, in some of these
cases it seemed to be a real case of a בעל דין
*Ba'al Din*, right, if you're a part owner of the ספר תורה
*Sefer Torah*, a part owner of the field, you are a
direct litigant, like it's your case. If however it's the case for
example I gave my half to Bobby, but I will indirectly benefit
because if Joe comes to collect the debt he'll be able to
get it from the half I sold to Bobby, I'm not a
direct בעל דין *Ba'al Din*, it's no longer my field, I'm not
protecting my money, but I am an indirect beneficiary of what will
be judged, and that's called a נוגע בעדות nogea be-eidus. *Nogei'a Be'edut*.
Okay, so what is and so that's interesting, you hear the conceptual
difference? Whether you're the direct person that's going to lose as a
result, your money is being taken away or you're winning directly money
is given to you, or no, you're somebody else's losing or winning,
but you will indirectly benefit or lose as a result. So one
is a בעל דין *Ba'al Din* and the other נוגע בעדות *Nogei'a
Be'edut*. So what ראב"ד *Ra'avad* says is this is a very formalistic
type of an approach, but what the ראב"ד *Ra'avad* says is, is
if you are a נוגע בעדות *Nogei'a Be'edut* then you were פסול
*pasul*, and if you started as a נוגע בעדות *Nogei'a Be'edut* you
can't be כשר *kosher* later on, because once you had that פסול
*pasul* label attached to you, you remain פסול *pasul*. But if you
started as a litigant, as a בעל דין *Ba'al Din*, you're not
a פסול עד pasul ed *pasul ed*. You're not an עד ed
*ed* at all. A litigant is not a witness, like these are
different roles, okay? So because a litigant is not fundamentally, it's not
like you're a פסול עד *pasul ed*, you're a non-עד *ed*. And
therefore, ironically, if you started as an actual principal, maybe that would
be a good word, principal, then and then you became you divested
yourself of the property, then you could be כשר *kosher* because you
never started your history as a פסול עד *pasul ed*, you started
your history as a non-עד *ed*. So it's ironic of course because
in that case you have a bigger stake and then you're allowed
to testify later. But anyway, but this becomes a Fascinating area for
ראשונים to discuss what are the parameters of תחילתו וסופו בכשרות? Yes.
Is the reason that's your תחילתו פסול וסופו בכשרות techilaso pasul vesofo
be-kashrus that you're now okay, is it because
we're worried that when you witnessed the event you'll be biased, right,
or is it on the other end that when you're testifying that
we're worried that you're going to—in other words, right—so some of that
might have a lot to do with this, but both of those
variations that you spoke about, did you see it in a way
that was through your own lens, or are you now intentionally—that might
have a lot to do with תוספות's difference between whether it's ממון
mamon or not, you know, as a relative, you know, you saw
something—anyway, but also both of those are very pragmatic types of concerns.
The ראב"ד's idea was not pragmatic, was a purely formalistic. He says
a פסול עד is worse than a non-עד even though a non-עד
has a bigger stake,
right? But yeah, so I have to go on because we only
have five minutes and at least we're going to turn the דף.
daf. Okay, השומר שכר זה לזה. Hashomer sachar zeh lazeh. All right,
that's a nice short דף-ish. daf Okay
so, Bobby and I are partners on this field. I say Bobby,
you watch this field, I gotta go take care of some personal
business, and while—or let's make it something that's easier to imagine, or
whatever—she falls asleep on the job, sorry Bobby, and came in people,
they completely tore up the whole ground because she wasn't sort of
watching when she should have been watching. So
obviously her half, she lost, but how about do I say I
suffer my half? No. Since she was watching it, even though she
was watching her half for herself, since she was watching my—again, there's
no line between it, she's watching the whole field, but she's doing
it all by herself—so on the 50 percent that's mine, okay, she
is a שומר שכר shomer sachar and she has to reimburse me
for my loss. Alright, so the גמרא says ואמאי שמירה בבעלים היא?
v'amai shemirah b'ba'alim hi? Now the גמרא says why? Isn't this שמירה
בבעלים? shemirah b'ba'alim? שמירה בבעלים Shemirah b'ba'alim means if you're watching for
me but I am in your service during that time, during the
time when the שמירה shemirah began, you are free from all liability.
So the גמרא assumes if Bobby is watching this field over here
in Riverdale that we jointly owned, and I'm watching the field that
we jointly owned in New Jersey at the same time, okay, we're
splitting up our—splitting it up. So when she's watching, I'm in her
service because I'm also watching her half over in New Jersey. Okay,
so she has no liability because I'm working for her, she's working
for me and I'm working for her all at the same time.
So the גמרא says אמר רב פפא דאמר ליה שמור לי היום
ואני אשמור לך למחר. Amar Rappa d'amar lei shemor li hayom ani
eshmor lecha l'machar. No no no. We're not doing it at the
same time. Today is all Bobby's day. I'm off today. And since
I'm off today, I'm not in her service today. What makes her
a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? Since I am going to swap, I'm
going to pay her for her watching for me today, because I'm
going to watch her tomorrow, which is her day off. So since
we're essentially paying each other with our service, okay, then when it's
Bobby's day, she's a שומר שכר shomer sachar and she has to
therefore pay me for any loss that happens to my half of
the field—I mean again, it's not a specific half, but for that
50 percent. Okay, so now we are done with unpacking שמואל's Shmuel
statement. Let's at least begin the next line in the גמרא. תנו
רבנן מכר לו בית מכר לו שדה אין מעיד לו עליה מפני
שאחריותו עליו. Tanu rabanan machar lo bayis machar lo sadeh ein me'id
lo aleha mipnei she-achrayuso alav. Okay, so now we're getting back to
this question about נוגע בעדות. And this is going to be very
complicated, so we're going to just put out the case there and
we're going to unpack it tomorrow. Okay, if I go ahead and
I sell my field or my house to David here, and then
some claims come that say that it's a stolen field, I never
owned it, so David doesn't own it because I never owned it,
I cannot testify to say that it's legitimate. All right, why that
David really owns it? מפני שאחריותו עליו mipnei she-achrayuso alav because I
have a responsibility for it. What does that mean I have a
responsibility for it? It's not clear. Presumably it means that if it
gets taken from David, I'll have to reimburse him. So therefore I'm
a direct beneficiary of saying that it still belongs to David. מכר
לו פרה מכר לו טלית מעיד לו עליה. machar lo parah machar
lo tallis me'id lo aleha. Let's say I sold David a cow
or a
garment and then there was a claim that it was stolen, I
can testify. Why? מפני שאין אחריותו עליו mipnei she-ein achrayuso alav because
I have no liability. Now, what do you mean I have no
liability? Meaning, if it turns out that it genuinely was stolen, it
was a מקח טעות. mekach ta'os. I never legitimately sold it to
David. So even if I don't formally accept insurance—right, insurance for fields
are because of cases in which it's taken away even though I
was a legitimate owner. But if I was never a legitimate owner,
then without even formally accepting insurance, I have to reimburse David, right?
It was a
מקח טעות, mekach ta'os, I sold him a bag of goods. So
the גמרא says מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shena reisha
u-mai shena seifa? What's the difference? Right? Either way I benefit by
testifying that it's David's so then I don't have to reimburse David
when somebody claims that the whole thing was stolen and I never
was a legitimate owner. So we are now going to stop here
and tomorrow we're going to get into the גמרא trying to have
some. So we are now going to stop here and tomorrow we're
going to get into the גמרא trying to have some very creative
interpretations of this statement to explain why one case I can be
a witness and one I cannot. So to be continued.